So the public disclosure of dirtyc0w or CVE-2016-5195 just happened.
来吧，脏牛 或CVE-2016-5195 的公开教学，正式开始。
This vulnerability is ancient, and allows a regular user on a system to perform a local
此漏洞很古老，允许系统上的普通用户，
privilege escalation and become root.
执行本地特权升级，并成为根。
I want to show it to you, explore how it works and generally talk about it.
我想向你们展示它，并探索它是如何工作的，谈论它的一般性。
Let’s cut right to the chase and start by looking at the provided proof-of-concept exploit.
让我们直接切入主题，从提供的概念验证入手。
I have here a vulnerable Ubuntu system where I can downloa and compile the exploit.
这里有一个易受攻击的Ubuntu系统，我可以下载并编译该漏洞。
Then I create a file owned by root to that I as a normal user can’t write to.
然后我创建了一个根权限，拥有的文件，作为普通用户我不能写入。
I can read it, but not write.
我可以读，但不能写。
This is true for many files on the file system like for example the ping binary.
对于文件系统上的许多文件，例如：ping二进制文件来说，权限都是差不多的。
ping belongs to root and has the setuid bit set.
Ping属于根权限，并且设置了setuid位。
This means anybody can execute it and it will run as root, but ping doesn’t do much except
这意味着，任何人都可以执行它，它将作为根权限运行，
sending out some networking traffic.
但是，ping除了发送一些网络流量，不能做更多了。
So our root file we just created resembles a file or binary like ping.
所以，我们刚刚创建的根文件，类似于 ping。
It’s owned by root and we can’t write to it.
属于根权限，我们(普通用户)是无法写入。
Now, when we execute dirtyc0w, and pass it the root file and specify a string we want
现在，当我们执行 dirtyc0w，并将根文件传递给它，并指定一个我们想要写入的字符串时，
to write, we can observe, that the string got written to the file.
我们可以观察到，字符串是被写入了文件。
We, as a regular user of the system, have written to a root file, that we don’t have
作为系统的普通用户，我们确实对一个根文件写入了，
write access to.
但是我们却没有写入访问权限。
This is insane.
这太疯狂了。
Now imagine we would have written a backdoor into the ping binary, we could become root
现在，假设我们已经在ping二进制文件中，编写了一个后门的话，
anytime.
我们随时都能成为根用户。
Without knowing the password of root.
不需要知道根的密码。
Now let’s try to understand the exploit code.
现在，让我们试着理解漏洞代码。
Let’s check out main() first where the code starts.
让我们先检查一下 main() 代码的起始位置。
So first it opens the file we want to write to as READ_ONLY.
因此，首先它将以只读(READ_ONLY)方式，打开要写入的文件。
Next comes a call to mmap().
接下来调用 mmap() 。
Mmap is used to create a new mapped memory segment in the current process.
mmap 用于在当前进程中，创建新的映射内存段。
One of these parameters can be a file descriptor and in this case it’s the READ_ONLY file
其中一个参数可以是文件描述符，在本例中，
owned by root.
就是根用户拥有的那个只读文件。
This means it maps the file into a new memory area.
这意味着，它将文件映射到一个新的内存区域。
Also the permission flags show, that this new memory area is READ_ONLY.
权限标志也显示，这个新的内存区域是只读的。
So far so good.
到现在为止，都还行。
The other important flag is the MAP_PRIVATE flag.
另一个重要标志，是 MAP_PRIVATE 标志。
The comment here is copied from the man page of mmap and it states, that this creates a
这里的注释，是从mmap的手册页复制的，它指出，
private copy-on-write mapping.
这将创建一个，copy-on-wirte(复制) 映射。
Or short C.O.W, cow.
或者，简写 C.O.W，牛。
This is where one part of the name for this vulnerability is from.
这是此漏洞名称，的一部分来源。
With this flag, mmap doesn’t copy the whole content of the file into memory, mmap maps
使用此标志，mmap不会将文件的全部内容，复制到内存中，
the file into your memory.
mmap 是将文件映射到您的内存。
This is awesome because you don’t need huge amounts of RAM to load a copy of the file,
这太棒了，因为您不需要大量的RAM，来加载文件副本，
you just directly read from the file on disk.
您可以直接从磁盘上的文件中读取。
Or relatively directly, we will learn more about memory in a second
或者相对直接地，我们将在一秒钟内，了解更多关于内存的信息。
And copy-on-write means, that if you were to write to this memory segment, you would
而 copy-on-write 意味着，如果你要写入这个内存段，
then create a copy of it.
你要创建一个副本。
So eventhough the file was mapped as READ_ONLY, because of the private mapping we can write
因此，尽管文件被映射为只读，但由于我们有私有映射，
to a copy of it.
因此，我们可以对它的副本写入。
So the important takeaway here is, that mmap will map the root file directly into your
而重要的是，mmap将根文件直接映射到内存，
memory, and you can read the content of the file, or write to a COPY of it.
您可以读取文件的内容，也可以写入到，文件的副本。
The changes to your copy should not be propagated to the real underlaying file.
本来嘛，对副本的更改，是不应该传播到真正的源文件的。
It’s just for you
只能自娱自乐一下。
Next we start two threads that will run in parallel.
但是转机来了，接下来，我们启动两个并行运行的线程。
Dirtyc0w is a race condition vulnerability, this means certain events have to occur in
脏牛，是一个竞态条件漏洞，这意味着，一些事件，
a specific order, that are fairly unlikely to happen under normal circumstances.
必须以顺序发生，所以在正常情况下，该漏洞不太可能发生。
So you try to race against the probability of it not happenign.
所以你试着，与不可能发生的概率赛跑。
And you simply try it over and over again.
你只是一次又一次的尝试。
And maybe you get lucky.
也许你会走运。
So let’s see what the two threads are doing.
让我们看看这两个线程，在做什么。
The first thread is the madviseThread.
第一条线索是 madviseThread。
This thread uses the syscall madvise, which probably doesn’t stand for memory advise,
这个线程使用 syscall madvise，它的名字可不代表什么(memory advise)内存建议，
but mad advise, I think the marketing department failed here, naming this vulerability not
应该是，疯了(mad)的建议，我认为市场部在这里失败了，
mad cow, am I right?
‘疯牛(mad COW)’这一漏洞名称也挺好的，是吧？
Ok. done with the dad jokes.
好啊。开够了父亲玩笑了。
So this syscall can be used for optimization reasons.
所以，这个 syscall 是用于优化的。
You can provide the kernel some information on how you intend to use a memory mapped area,
您可以向内核提供一些，关于如何使用内存映射区域的信息，
because there are different techniques how you handle caching, look ahead and so forth.
因为，在处理缓存时，有不同的技术，所以要向前看。
And the one advise we give the kernel is, that the memory area where we mapped the file
我们给内核的一个建议是，我们文件映射到的内存区域
to, or at least the first 100 byte, is probably not needed anytime soon.
或者至少是前100字节，可能不需要用在任何时间。
We say that with the MADV_DONTNEED flag, which stands for:
我们带上，MADV_DONTNEED 标志，它代表：
Do not expect access in the near future.
不希望在不久的将来，访问。
(For the time being, the application is finished with the given range, so the kernel can free
（目前，应用程序在给定范围内，完成，因此内核可以释放
resources associated with it.)
与之相关的资源。）
Subsequent accesses of pages in this range will succeed, but will result in reloading
此范围内的页面 Subsequent 访问将成功，但将导致重新加载
of the memory contents from the underlying mapped file.
来自底层映射文件的内存内容。
The last sentence is key to the exploit.
最后一句是漏洞的关键。
Otherwise not much else happening here.
不然，这里就不会发生什么了。
The other thread, procselfmemThread, opens the file /proc/self/mem.
另一个线程 procselfmemThread，打开了文件 /proc/self/mem。
This is a special file and I try to explain really quick.
这是一个特殊的文件，我试着快速解释下。
So /proc is a so called pseudo filesystem.
/proc 是一个所谓的伪文件系统。
In fact most resources on linux are managed as “files”.
实际上，Linux上的大多数资源，都是作为“文件”管理的。
So you should always see “files” in quotation marks when talking about them.
所以在谈论“文件”时，你应该总是看到引号中的“files”。
Imagine a file just to be something, you can read from, or write to.
想象一个文件，只是某种东西，你可以读，也可以写。
So this could be printer, and writing to the printer “file” could result in an actual
所以，这可能是打印机，当写入“文件”这个打印机时，
physical printer printing the string on a piece of paper.
结果会是，一台物理打印机，在一张纸上打印字符串。
So /proc does not really contain “files” in the common sense.
所以，/proc在常理上，并不真正包含“files”。
They refer to something more general, most importantly for our case, something you can
它们指的是更一般的东西，对于我们的情况而言最为重要，
read and write to.
是一些你可以读写的东西。
So in this case /proc/self refers to special “files” provided for the current process.
因此，在本例中/proc/self指的是，为当前进程提供的特殊“文件”。
So every process will have it’s own /proc/self.
所以，每个进程都有自己的/proc/self。
And in there is a “file” called mem, which is a representation of the current process’s
其中有一个名为 mem 的“文件”，它表示当前进程的
memory.
内存。
So you could theoretically read your own process’s memory by reading from this file.
所以，理论上你可以通过读取这个文件，来读取你自己进程的内存。
Now in this case, the exploit WRITES to this file in a loop.
在这种情况下，漏洞会在一个循环中，写入该文件。
So first it performs a seek, which moves the current cursors to the start of the file that
因此，首先它执行一个查找，将当前光标，移动到文件的开头，
we mapped into memory.
所谓的开头，还是在映射内存中的。
And then it writes the string we pass via the program arguments to it.
然后，它会写入我们传递的程序字符串参数。
So this will trigger a copy of the memory, so that we can write to it and see these changes.
所以，这将触发内存的一个副本，这样我们就可以写入它，并看到这些更改。
But remember, we will not write to the real underlaying file.
但请记住，我们不会写入真正的底层文件。
So if you would do these things once, or just isolated from eachother, probably nothing
所以，如果你只做一次这些事情，或者把操作分割开来，
would happen.
可能什么都不会发生。
Because that would be the expected result.
因为，要的就是预期结果。
But because there is a race condition issue somewhere, trying this over and over again
但是，因为在某个地方有一个竞态条件的问题，反复尝试这个后，
will create a weird edgecase, that usually doesn’t occur, but in this case tricks the
将创建一个奇怪的边缘，通常不会发生，
kernel into actually writing to the underlaying file.
但在这种情况下，会欺骗内核，确实地写入底层文件。
Now let’s have a look at the patch, because I think this is very interesting and not very
现在，让我们来看看这个补丁，因为我觉得这很有趣，也不是
big.
很大。
So in the commit message the author states that
所以在提交消息中，作者声明
This is an ancient bug that was actually attempted to be fixed once (badly) by me eleven years
这是一种古老的 bug ，我确实试图一次修复(不好啊)，在11年前的
ago in commit 4ceb5db9757a ("Fix get_user_pages() race for write access") but that was then
提交 4ceb5db9757a（“修复 get_user_pages() 在 write 访问的竞态”）中，但那时
undone due to problems on s390 by commit f33ea7f404e5 ("fix get_user_pages bug").
通过提交 f33ea7f4004e5（“修复 get_user_pages bug”），撤消S390上的问题。
So I’m a little bit disappointed here at my IBM friends, because they almost have a
所以，我对我的IBM朋友也有点失望，因为他们几乎都有
partial guilt here.
部分责任。
S390 is the architecture used by IBM mainfraimes, system z.
S390是 IBM Mainframes，System Z 使用的体系结构。
Anyhow, let’s have a quick look.
不管怎样，让我们快点看看。
The file that is patched belongs to the linux memory manager, hence the mm directory.
修补的文件属于 Linux内存管理器，因此，是 mm 目录。
And the file itself is called GUP, which stands for get_user_pages.
文件本身被称为 gup，它代表 get_user_pages (获取用户页面)）。
Vm stands for virtual memory and pte for page table entry.
vm 代表虚拟内存，pte 代表页面表格条目。
I think that should help a little bit to understand the code.
我认为这有助于理解代码。
So when you want to write to this mapped memory, the kernel has to copy it, because you are
So，当您想要写入这个映射内存时，内核必须复制它，
not allowed to write to the underlying file.
因为你不允许写入底层文件。
But a copy takes time.
但复制需要时间。
Now usually you do the copy once and you are fine, but in this case we call madvise with
现在通常你复印一次就可以了，但在这种情况下，我们调用 madvise 带上 DONTNEED 标志，
DONTNEED over and over again.
一遍又一遍地运行。
Let’s look this up in the code.
让我们在代码中，查找这个。
So if this flag is used, this function is executed.
因此，如果使用此标志，就执行此函数。
The kernel source code explains that the:
内核源代码解释了：
Application no longer needs these pages.
应用程序不再需要这些页面。
If the pages are dirty, it's OK to just throw them away.
如果页面脏了，把它们扔掉就可以了。
The app will be more careful about data it wants to keep.
这个应用程序会对它想要保存的数据，更加小心。
Be sure to free swap resources too.
还一定要释放交换资源。
I guess I quickly explain dirty.
我想我快速解释 脏 (dirty)了。
This is also where the other part of the name is from.
漏洞名称的另一部分来源。
When you read and write to disk you never do this directly, that would be wayyy to slow.
当您读写磁盘时，您永远不能直接这样做，速度会以某种方式，放慢。
So you cache, or buffer them.
所以，你会缓存，或缓冲它们。
This means you hold this data somewhere and at some point in time you write it to the
这意味着，您将此数据保存在某个位置，并在某个时间点，按时
disk.
写入磁盘。
Ok.
好啊。
So if you read data from disk into memory you can just leave it there in the cache for
因此，如果您将数据从磁盘，读取到内存中，
further reads.
你可以为近一步读取，把它们留在缓存。
BUT, if you want to write to the disk, you write it into this cache/buffer, but now you
但是，如果您想写入磁盘，您把(数据)写入，这个缓存/缓冲区，
have to tell the system, that this buffer got touched and is dirty now.
不过，现在您必须告诉系统，这个缓冲区被碰了，变脏了。
It’s not clean fresh memory anymore.
告诉系统，它不再是干净的新鲜内存了。
In this case the system has to make sure that the change is properly propagated to the underlaying
在这种情况下，系统必须确保更改，
physical memory.
正确传播到底层物理内存。
Let it be a file on disk or flash memory.
让它成为，磁盘或闪存上的文件。
So in this case, if you wrote to the copied mmaped memory, the memory page got flagged
因此，在本例中，如果您要写入复制的映射内存，
dirty.
则会把这个内存页标记上，dirty。
And because you tell the kernel now, that the page is not needed anymore, this means
因为你现在告诉内核，页面不再需要了，
you don’t care that the dirty page has not been written yet.
这意味着，你不在乎脏页是否，写出来。
You just toss it.
你只是扔了它。
So this madvise call causes the throwing away of this memory.
所以，这个 madvise 调用会让这些内存消失。
This means it’s not in any of the memory caches anymore.
这意味着，它不再存在于任何内存缓存中。
This is important for this exploit, because this means, everytime when we try to write
而这对该漏洞很重要，因为这意味着，
to it again, the copy of the memory might have been tossed.
每当我们试图写它，内存的副本可能已经被丢弃了。
So we have to re load a new copy from memory so we can write to it.
所以我，们必须从内存中，重新加载一个新的副本，这样我们才能写入它。
And creating this copy takes time.
而创建这个副本需要时间。
And this is the race condition, if the copy-on-write cycle is not complete yet.
正是这时，竞争条件发生了，如果 copy-on-write 周期还没有完成。
The patch added this function that checks if the copy-on-write is complete yet, and
补丁程序，添加了这个函数，来检查 copy-on-write 是否完成，
only then allows writing to it.
只有这样才允许写入。
To be honest, I don’t understand this code really to tell you why this snippet makes
老实说，我真的不理解这段代码，
sure that the copy on write is complete.
无法告诉你，为什么这段代码就能确保“copy-on-write”已完成。
But it added some additional checks, so I assume now it’s fine.
但它增加了一些额外的检查，所以我想现在可以了。
So here is the mental picture of our race condition.
这是我们竞态状况的思维图。
We constantly use madvise to drop any cached copy of the mapped file.
我们经常使用 madvise，删除映射文件的任何缓存副本。
And at the same time we try to write to it, which causes a copy of that memory.
同时，我们试图写入，而这导致了内存的复制。
Now in some rare condition, that can be hit very reliably by just trying over and over
此时，在一些竞态条件的作用下，只要反复尝试，就可以非常可靠地击中它，漏洞产生。
again, we perform the write to the memory, before the page table is updated to point
也就是，在页面表格更新，让我们指向新副本之前，
us to our copied version.
执行了对内存的写操作。
And we write to the real file instead of the copied memory.
我们就会对真实文件写入，而不是复制的版本(因为已经消失了，被 madvise)。
So the crazy thing about this vulnerability is, that it has been in the kernel for a very
关于这个漏洞的疯狂之处在于，它已经在内核中，存在了很长一段时间了。
long time.
长时间。
And it was even a known issue, according to the patch author, that had been attempted
根据补丁作者的说法，在尝试修补之前，
to be patched before.
这甚至是一个已知的问题。
So over time this apparently theoretical race condition got viable because our systems got
随着时间的推移，这个具有明确理论的竞态条件的实现变得很可行，
faster and faster.
因为我们的系统越来越快。
And Petr Matousek also states, that this was an 0day exploit used in the wild.
Petr Matousek也指出，这是一个在法外，使用的零日漏洞。
So there was a real threat.
所以有一个真正的威胁。
Now a bit of controversy.
现在，带有争议。
And this goes into the unresolved debate that has been going on for decates how to do vulnerability
进入了几十年来未解决的争论，就是如何进行漏洞披露
disclosure.
披露。
If you were the person who found this exploit in the wild, what would you do?
如果你是在法外，发现这一漏洞的人，你会怎么做？
The obvious arguments are:
一个有力观点是：
Full disclosure, because it was actively exploited, fully disclosing it right away would have
完全披露，因为这样它可以被积极响应，
not given advanced attackers anything new.
完全披露，让大家处于同一认知水平线，就不会给高级攻击者任何的新信息。
But the knowledge would have allowed system administrators to immediately patch their
但是，这些知识，是否能够让系统管理员
systems.
立即修复系统。
But on the other hand it is such an easy and widespread vulnerability, that a full disclosure
也就有了一个薄弱且普遍的弱点，
would have allowed armies of less skilled hackers to take advantage of it, until less
一个完全披露的漏洞，会让技术较差的黑客军队利用它，
professional sysadmins or private people could patch it.
直到专业的系统管理员或私人，去修补它。
On the otherside we have the responsible disclosure where you first contact the developers, create
完全的另一方面，就是责任披露，这里的第一步，要联系开发人员，
a fix, try to roll it out and then tell people afterwards.
给出一个解决办法，实际测试，然后再告诉人们。
The obvious arguments here are, you stopped professional sysadmins for hotpatching their
这里的有力论点是，您让专业系统管理员不能，
system quickly and leave them exposed for the ongoing attacks.
迅速对系统进行热修补，让其暴露在持续的攻击中。
Now I don’t know what is the best way.
对于我而言，我并不知道最好的方法是什么。
Both ways have advantages and disadvantages.
两种方法都有优缺点。
And it entirely depends on your threat model.
这完全取决于你的危险模型。
In general I lean slightly more towards full disclosure, because I like information to
一般来说，我更倾向于完全披露，
be free, though I myself do responsible disclosure because I’m a hypocrite.
可能是因为我喜欢信息的自由吧，尽管，我自己实际做的是负责披露，因为我是个 hypocrite。
I hope you liked this kind of exploit walkthrough video and that I could show you something
我希望，你喜欢这种漏洞演练的视频，
new and interesting.
可以给你看一些新颖有趣的东西。
If I said something wrong or you have additional info on why this exploit has to be triggered
如果我说了错误的话，或者你有关于为什么必须通过写入/proc/mem，
through a write to /proc/ mem and not directly writing to the address, please correct me
而不是直接写入地址，才能触发此漏洞的其他补充信息，请更正我的错误。
or post additional info in the comments below, so that other attentive viewers can benefit
或者在下面的评论中，发布补充信息，以便其他关注的观众，
from it.
可以受益。
Thanks.
谢谢。